all right
[Music]
increased public awareness and demand
for bad breath remedies has resulted in
a substantial growth of the breath
freshening industry and the saturation
of the market with breath improving
products such as mints chewing gum
breath sprays and pills the majority of
which have only a short-term masking
effect on bad breath and are essentially
ineffective well what can we do could it
be as simple as swishing with some water
take morning breath malouda's breath
upon Awakening after a night's sleep is
a common condition known as morning bad
breath the most common cause of bad
breath in general is the degradation of
protein and protein fragments by
microorganisms residing on the tongue
and teeth particularly the sulfur
containing amino acids cysteine and
methionine that are broken down into
volatile sulfur compounds like the
rotten egg gas hydrogen sulfide
approximately 50 of the adult population
has early morning concentrations of
these compounds in mouth air that exceed
the threshold of objection ability
established by the organoleptic panel
what does that mean
the organellectic method is considered
the gold standard in the examination of
breath Mal odor basically all this means
is some examiner sniffs the air exhaled
from the mouth and nose and subjectively
defines the presence or absence of odor
and what people's morning breath are
sniffed about half exceed the threshold
of objection ability why what causes it
a dry mouth
low salivary flow particularly during
the night creates like a stagnant Pond
effect favorable for bacterial
proliferation and putrefaction and so to
reduce morning bad breath you may read
suggestions that rinsing with or
drinking water upon Awakening is
effective but you don't know
until you put it to the test the effect
of water on morning bad breath a
randomized clinical trial one group was
randomized to rinse their mouth with a
tablespoon of water and the other to
drink about a cup and they both worked
significant improving bad breath with no
apparent differences between them though
they didn't have a control group and it
would have been interesting to see how
much their breath improved just being
awake with their normal salivary flow
after drinking and eating in the morning
morning breaths tends to disappear
people brush their teeth in the morning
thinking that's going to help but that
may only reduce rotten egg gas levels 30
percent whereas eating breakfast Works
twice as well a 60 drop in hydrogen
sulfide levels the mechanical action of
chewing stimulates the flow of slav and
the passage of food over the surface of
the tongue removes the putrified surface
film thus simulating the action of
tongue brushing well if it's a matter of
the amount of tongue coding there is how
about actively brushing your tongue like
you would your teeth and you get close
to a 70 drop suggesting the tongue is
the major source of the stinky gases
other studies though show no benefit to
tongue brushing on oral odor in both
adults and children
the researcher suggests maybe the gag
reflex kept people from doing a better
job
what about tongue scraping in this study
they compared tooth brushing brushing
plus flossing brushing plus scraping or
all three they found that adding
flossing didn't really seem to affect
morning breath and that tongue scraping
won the day against tooth brushing
suggesting that tongue cleaning may be
the most important hygienic procedure to
reduce morning bad breath
this is not to suggest tooth brushing
doesn't help with bad breath here they
had people stop brushing their teeth for
five days but continue to floss and
tongue scrape all while doing their
fancy organoleptic technique where they
blew through a straw at some poor
examiner's nose and despite all that
scraping and flossing their breath got
worse when they stopped brushing
what about tongue brushing versus tongue
scraping researchers compiled all the
randomized controlled trials comparing
different methods of tongue cleaning to
reduce mouth odor in adults with
halitosis and
the tongue scraping was found to be
slightly more effective than tongue
brushing perhaps the fact that the width
of a toothbrush is smaller than the
width of a regular tongue scraper might
make it less effective or removing
loosened debris from the tongue
[Music]
foreign